<points_tutorial>

  <point>
    <name>Avoid Problems</name>
    <goal>To reduce the number of hassles so you can focus on what is most important.</goal>
    <explanation>The easiest way to deal with a problem is to avoid it.[br]You avoid problems by preventing them, not pretending they don&#8217;t exist.</explanation>
    <tool>
      <name>Reduce stress</name>
      <goal>To avoid a problem by reducing stress.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to reduce stress</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>Children act out in many ways when they feel stressed. Look for ways to simplify the child&#8217;s life or provide outlets for stress.</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]Feed Adam before he is starved. Put him down immediately when he is done.[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;Make sure she gets enough exercise.[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;Make sure Chad has unstructured time to &#8220;goof off.&#8221;</example>
    </tool>
    <tool>
      <name>Change things</name>
      <goal>To avoid a problem by changing the environment or the schedule.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to change things</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>Look at when and why the problem behavior occurs. Change the environment (add or remove something) to increase desired behavior or decrease unwanted behavior.</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]Put an old shower curtain under his highchair.[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;Eat earlier so Becky won&#8217;t be so hungry.[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;Buy a bright red trash basket so it is easier to notice.</example>
    </tool>
    <tool>
      <name>Two yeses</name>
      <goal>To teach children what they may do.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to give two yeses</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>Tells the child what he or she [i]may[/i] do. Suggest changing the tool, time, or location to find acceptable behavior.</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]&#8220;You may eat your food, or raise your arms to ask to get down.&#8221;[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;&#8220;You may speak pleasantly or whine in a different room.&#8221;[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;&#8220;You may empty the trash by yourself or ask for help.&#8221;</example>
    </tool>
  </point>

  <point>
    <name>Respond to Cooperation</name>
    <goal>To increase good behavior by noticing it and acknowledging it.</goal>
    <explanation>People see what they expect to see. If you expect to see bad behavior, you will see more bad behavior than good behavior.[br]To increase a desired behavior, figure out what you want the child [i]to do or say[/i] instead of what they are doing.</explanation>
    <tool>
      <name>Attention</name>
      <goal>To encourage behavior you want by noticing it.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to give attention</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>Notice behavior you want. Give verbal or nonverbal recognition.</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]Include Adam in table conversation while he behaves appropriately.[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;When Becky talks pleasantly, smile and give her attention.[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;Give Chad a &#8220;thumbs-up&#8221; sign as he takes the trash out.</example>
    </tool>
    <tool>
      <name>Praise</name>
      <goal>To encourage behavior you want by commenting on it.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to give praise</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>Effective praise is specific, immediate, and sincere.</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]Say, &#8220;Wow! You asked to get down.&#8221; And put her down right away[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;Say, &#8220;You used a very pleasant voice.&#8221;[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;Say, &#8220;You remembered to take the trash out by yourself. Well done.&#8221;</example>
    </tool>
    <tool>
      <name>Rewards</name>
      <goal>To encourage desired behavior by rewarding it.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to give rewards</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>Decide what you want the child [i]to do[/i]. Reward the behavior as soon as the child does it. Use something the child wants or needs (for example: stars, stickers, small toys, tokens, time, hugs or privileges).</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]Give a big hug when he says he is done.[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;The first three times Becky asks with a pleasant voice, give her what she requests.[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;Say, &#8220;Each time you take the trash out without reminding, I&#8217;ll give you a star. When you have five stars, you may trade them for a &#8220;task excused&#8221; ticket you may use when you want to.&#8221;</example>
    </tool>
  </point>

  <point>
    <name>Acknowledge Feelings</name>
    <goal>To reflect children&#8217;s feelings without judging or agreeing with them.</goal>
    <explanation>Feelings are neither good nor bad. Feelings and behaviors are different from one another. Feelings are on the inside. Behavior is what you do with those feelings. You can express feelings in both healthy and unhealthy ways.[br]Accept children&#8217;s feelings. Show them how to express them in healthy ways.</explanation>
    <tool>
      <name>Simple listening</name>
      <goal>To acknowledge feelings simply by listening.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to do simple listening</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>Listen. Respond with neutral statements like: &#8220;Uh-huh,&#8221; &#8220;Okay,&#8221; &#8220;Yeah,&#8221; &#8220;Tell me more,&#8221; &#8220;Really? &#8220; &#8221;Oh,&#8221; &#8220;Hmm,&#8221; etc.</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]Not age-appropriate[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;When she whines, say, &#8220;Oh.&#8221; &#8220;Really?&#8221;[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;Listen when Chad complains and respond appropriately with &#8220;Humm,&#8221; &#8220;I see,&#8221; &#8220;Tell me more.&#8221;</example>
    </tool>
    <tool>
      <name>Active listening</name>
      <goal>To reflect the feelings and the situation.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to do active listening</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>Reflect the feelings and describe the situation. Active listening is nonjudgmental, asks no questions, gives no advice. It leaves the problem with the child.</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]Say, &#8220;It&#8217;s boring [i](feeling)[/i] waiting to get down while we talk [i](situation)[/i].&#8221;[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;&#8220;Sounds like you&#8217;re disappointed [i](feeling)[/i] that you can&#8217;t have a cookie now [i](situation)[/i].&#8221;[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;&#8220;I wonder if it&#8217;s annoying [i](feeling)[/i] having to take the trash out right after supper [i](situation)[/i]?&#8221;</example>
    </tool>
    <tool>
      <name>Grant in fantasy</name>
      <goal>To acknowledge feelings and support the child.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to grant in fantasy</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>Give in pretend what you cannot do in real life. Talk about the choices you would make and how it would feel.</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]Not age-appropriate[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;Say, &#8220;Wouldn&#8217;t it be fun if cookies were very nutritious and you had to eat a bowlful each day.&#8221;[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;Say, &#8220;Wouldn&#8217;t it be fun if you could snap your fingers and the trash would run out and hop in the garbage can.&#8221;</example>
    </tool>
  </point>

  <point>
    <name>Set Reasonable Limits</name>
    <goal>To establish clear boundaries and let kids test them.</goal>
    <explanation>Children need reasonable limits or rules. Rules can be negotiable (some flexibility) or non-negotiable (no exceptions).[br]Normal children test limits. Persistent children test limits many more times. Remember, persistence is an excellent adult trait. You want to guide it, not crush it.[br]Before you make a rule, decide what you will do if the child tests or challenges it.</explanation>
    <tool>
      <name>Clear limits</name>
      <goal>To let children know what behavior is acceptable.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to set clear limits</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>Create age appropriate rules. State rule clearly (positive and specific). Establish consequences. Follow through!</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]Food is for eating.[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;Two ideas: Speak pleasantly. [i]Or[/i] No food 30 minutes before meals.[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;Trash taken out before 7:00.</example>
    </tool>
    <tool>
      <name>Consequences</name>
      <goal>To clarify the child&#8217;s choices when he or she wants to breaks a rule.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to give consequences</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>State rule and what will happen if it is broken. Effective consequences are related to behavior and are immediate. [i]Both[/i] choices in the consequence are acceptable to parent.</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]&#8220;If you throw food, you are done eating.&#8221; Remove food and put him down.[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;&#8220;If you whine, the answer will be no.&#8221;[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;&#8220;Chores and privileges go together. If you forget to take the trash out before 7:00 P.M., you lose a privilege that evening.&#8221; A privilege might be computer use, TV, reading in bed, etc.</example>
    </tool>
    <tool>
      <name>A better way</name>
      <goal>To find a solution that is acceptable to both parent and child. Shares power.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to find a better way</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>State your preference and your child&#8217;s preference, and [i]ask the child[/i] for a way that works for both of you. (Children are more likely to accept ideas they suggest.)</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]Not age-appropriate, use two yeses instead.[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;&#8220;I want you to speak pleasantly. You want to whine. How can we both be happy?&#8221;[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;&#8220;My way is you take the trash out right after supper. You want to take it out late. What is a better way?&#8221;</example>
    </tool>
  </point>

  <point>
    <name>Teach New Skills</name>
    <goal>To offer children the skills they need for your family and the larger world.</goal>
    <explanation>Many children have &#8220;blind spots&#8221; &#8212; skills or information you expect a child to have but he or she does not.[br]The skills may be simple, like putting on clothes. Or, they may be complex, like remembering things or controlling their anger.</explanation>
    <tool>
      <name>Modeling</name>
      <goal>To encourage a behavior by demonstrating it.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to do modeling</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>Young children are natural mimics. To model a skill or behavior, do [i]exactly[/i] what you want the child to do. Modeling is enhanced by explaining what you are doing and why you are doing it.</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]When you are done eating, say, &#8220;All done,&#8221; and push your plate away.[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;Model beginning to whine, then say, &#8220;That&#8217;s whining, I&#8217;ll speak pleasantly.&#8221;[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;As you start dinner, say, &#8220;I don&#8217;t feel like cooking tonight, but it is my job. The sooner I start, the sooner I&#8217;ll be done.&#8221;</example>
    </tool>
    <tool>
      <name>Shaping</name>
      <goal>To teach a behavior by dividing it into small steps.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to do shaping</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>Decide what skills a child needs to do the desired behavior. Divide the skill or task into small steps. This can be used for simple tasks like putting on a coat, or more complex ones like playing pleasantly with a sibling.</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i](1) Ask Adam to raise his arms when he is done eating. (2) Ask him to say &#8220;all done.&#8221;[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;(1) Distinguish between a whine and a pleasant voice. (2) Notice she is whining and then speak pleasantly. (3) Start speaking pleasantly.[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;(1) Help parent take the trash out. (2) Take trash out when reminded. (3) Take trash out without reminding.</example>
    </tool>
    <tool>
      <name>Re-do it right</name>
      <goal>To practice appropriate behavior.</goal>
      <how_to_title>How to re-do it right</how_to_title>
      <how_to_text>Decide what behavior you want. When the child uses unacceptable behavior, help your child re-do the action using appropriate behavior.</how_to_text>
      <example>[i]Toddler&#8212;[/i]Put food back on plate and remind Adam to ask to get down.[br][i]Preschooler[/i]&#8212;When Becky whines, pleasantly say, &#8220;Oops, that was whining. Start again pleasantly.&#8221;[br][i]School-aged[/i]&#8212;&#8220;Chad, it&#8217;s after 7:00 P.M. and you walked by the trash without taking it out. It&#8217;s time to re-do it right.&#8221;</example>
    </tool>
  </point>

</points_tutorial>
<!-- Modified November 02, 2017, Compiled November 02, 2017 -->
