<daily_tip>
  <tip>
    <text>What you notice is what you get.</text>
    <explanation>The more you notice and comment on a behavior, the more the behavior will be repeated. This is true whether you are praising a behavior or complaining (nagging) about it.[br]Notice what you comment on. Is it behavior you want more of or less of? To improve a child&#8217;s behavior, look for and comment on the behavior you want.</explanation>
    <link>[i]STAR Parenting Tales and Tools[/i], page 88</link>
  </tip>

  <tip>
    <text>Praise like a sportscaster.</text>
    <explanation>A sportscaster describes the play (action) for the listener so they know what is happening. Praise describes what you like for the child.[br]Specific praise is most effective. &#8220;You closed the door gently when you came in.&#8221; &#8220;You asked your sister for a turn with the markers.&#8221;[br]Use descriptions as a sports caster might call the plays to let the child know what you like.</explanation>
    <link>[i]STAR Parenting Tales and Tools[/i]</link>
  </tip>

  <tip>
    <text>When you give attention, a child feels connected.</text>
    <explanation>Children need to feel connected. Attention is one way to connect. Attention is nonverbal, which distinguishes it from praise.[br]Five ways to give attention are:[br] * proximity&#8212;being near, watching[br] * making eye contact, smiling[br] * loving touches, hugs, back rubs[br] * gestures (high five, or OK sign)[br] * rituals (celebration dinners, etc.)[br]These actions convey caring and connectedness to your child.</explanation>
    <link>[i]STAR Parenting Tales and Tools[/i]</link>
  </tip>

  <tip>
    <text>Quality time reduces unwanted behavior.</text>
    <explanation>Research has found that fifteen to twenty minutes of quality time a day dramatically reduces obnoxious behavior in children.[br]Effective quality time must be:[br] * [i]One-on-one.[/i] You are focused on the child (not distracted by phone, planning, or other activities).[br] * [i]Child-directed.[/i] Adult follows the child&#8217;s lead in play.[br] * [i]Predictable.[/i] Happens at the same time day after day. The child can depend on getting his needs met.</explanation>
    <link>[i]STAR Parenting Tales and Tools[/i]</link>
  </tip>

  <tip>
    <text>You can control how your child gets attention, not whether he gets it.</text>
    <explanation>When a child wants attention badly enough she&#8217;ll do whatever she must to get it. There is a saying, if a child can&#8217;t get a kiss he will take a kick.[br][i]How do you want your child to interrupt you when you wish to be left alone?[/i] Some parents like their child to: &#9829;Ask for a hug. &#9829;Put a hand on their arm. &#9829;Wait quietly beside you. &#9829;Say, &#8220;Excuse me.&#8221; &#9829;Offer to help.</explanation>
    <link>[i]STAR Parenting Tales and Tools[/i]</link>
  </tip>

  <tip>
    <text>Look for &#8220;good&#8221; behavior.</text>
    <explanation>We often miss good behavior because we are too busy with our own activities or we really don&#8217;t know what we are looking for.[br]Here are some ways other parents have used to find good behavior:[br] * plan time to look for it,[br] * ask others for examples[br] * look for the behavior in other kids[br] * visualize your child with the behavior you want[br] * look for the seeds of what you want.</explanation>
    <link>[i]STAR Parenting Tales and Tools[/i]</link>
  </tip>

  <tip>
    <text>Praise [u]effort[/u] as well as success.</text>
    <explanation>Kids need praise for [i]effort[/i] as well as success. When you praise primarily success, children often conclude that things should come easily to them. When things are hard, they may be reluctant to try new things or get discouraged if it is hard. Some examples:[br] * You had a hard time balancing the block on the tower. You tried, and tried, and tried &#8217;til you did it.[br] * You got a 95 on the math test. The effort you spent practicing helped.</explanation>
    <link>[i]STAR Parenting Tales and Tools[/i]</link>
  </tip>

  <tip>
    <text>Try the power of &#8220;and.&#8221;</text>
    <explanation>The English language has several [i]gotchas[/i] for parents &#8212; the word &#8220;but&#8221; is one. [i]But[/i] acts as an eraser for the first half of the sentence.[br]Think how these two sentences might sound to a young child &#8212;[br] - I love you [i]but[/i] you can&#8217;t come.[br] - I love you [i]and[/i] you can&#8217;t come.[br]With the first sentence, kids usually hear only &#8220;you can&#8217;t come!&#8221; With the second, they hear they are loved and they can&#8217;t come.[br]Use the power of &#8220;and&#8221; and &#8220;but&#8221; wisely.</explanation>
    <link></link>
  </tip>

  <tip>
    <text>Some kids don&#8217;t like praise.</text>
    <explanation>For whatever reason, some children do not want praise. Look at the type of praise you give. If the praise is judgmental or exaggerated, she may not want it. If so, try appreciative, descriptive, or reflective praise.[br]If those are unwanted, you can try:[br] * [i]Nonverbal attention[/i]&#8212;giving a high five, a smile, or a back rub.[br] * [i]Indirect praise[/i]&#8212;saying kind things about your child to someone else within the child&#8217;s hearing.[br] * [i]Reported praise[/i]&#8212;passing on a compliment from someone else.</explanation>
    <link>[i]STAR Parenting Tales and Tools[/i]</link>
  </tip>

  <tip>
    <text>Try Grandma&#8217;s rule.</text>
    <explanation>Grandma&#8217;s rule is a way to clarify expectations. For example: &#8220;[i]When[/i] you put your blocks on the shelf, [i]then[/i] we will read a story.&#8221; Note, this is not a choice. It is a gentle expectation.[br]On the other hand, when you say, &#8220;[i]If[/i] you put your blocks on the shelf, [i]then[/i] we will read a story,&#8221; you offer the child a choice. If he does not want a story, he doesn&#8217;t need to put away the blocks.[br]The [i]when/then[/i] structure implies an expectation. The [i]if/then[/i] structure implies a choice.</explanation>
    <link>[i]Without Spanking or Spoiling[/i]</link>
  </tip>

  <tip>
    <text>Is &#8220;Okay?&#8221; okay?</text>
    <explanation>&#8220;It&#8217;s time to leave. Okay?&#8221;[br]&#8216;Okay&#8217; asks for acceptance or agreement. If the child hears the word as a command and complies, it&#8217;s fine. However, if she hears the word as a genuine question and answers &#8220;No,&#8221; you face a dilemma.[br]* [i]You can ignore the child and assert yourself:[/i] &#8220;Well, it&#8217;s time to go. Put your coat on.&#8221; This often leaves the child thinking she is of little value as her answer was worthless.[br]* Or, [i]You can backpedal and respect the child.[/i] &#8220;Okay. We can go in 2[br]minutes.&#8221; This only slows you a bit.[br]Is &#8220;Okay our choice.</explanation>
    <link></link>
  </tip>
</daily_tip>
<!-- Modified November 02, 2017, Compiled November 02, 2017 -->
